# Mashaan Alshammari

Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

mashaan.awad@outlook.com







I am a machine learning researcher, working on graph clustering and deep learning problems. Previously, I held academic positions in an Australian institute and a Saudi university, where I designed computer science courses for both master's and undergraduate levels.

Last Updated: July 2024

#### **EDUCATION**

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Computer Science, The University of Sydney,

Thesis title: "Graph Filtering and Automatic Parameter Selection for Efficient Spectral Clustering."

Master of Science, Computer Science, King Fahd University of Petroleum and Minerals (KFUPM),

Thesis title: "Human In-Place Action Recognition using Combination of Kinect Data Streams."

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Hail,

2017 — 2021

2013 - 2016

2005 — 2010

### **SKILLS**

Social media

Research & Development Technical Curriculum design 1st author in 13+ research papers, 70+ verified reviews on Web of Science.

Previously Java and Matlab, currently using Python's ML libraries (pytorch, jax, flax, PyG, scikit-learn). Designing CS courses following Australian Qualifications Framework (AQF) and Saudi Arabia's NCAAA. 12K+ views and 250+ watch hours for my YouTube educational videos; 40+ stars on my Github.

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Curriculum Development Collaborator Sydney Polytechnic Institute

Jul 2023 — Present Sydney, Australia

- · Participated in curriculum development for a Master of Data Science and Bachelor of Computing.
- Designed the outline and planner documents for courses: Database Systems (U211), Cybersecurity and Information Assurance (U312), and Full-stack development (U322).

# Machine Learning Researcher Freelance

Jun 2022 — Present Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

- · Working on machine learning research with researchers from the University of Sydney and KFUPM.
- Our research focuses on Graph Convolutional Network (GCN) and Unsupervised Domain Adaptation (UDA).
- · Designed experiments using python ML libraries (pytorch, jax, flax, scikit-learn).

## Assistant Professor University of Hail

Jan 2021 — Jun 2022 Hail, Saudi Arabia

- Participated in curriculum design and lecturing for multiple graduate and undergraduate computer science courses.
- Adapted new teaching strategies to teach the following courses: data structures (ICS202), advanced database (ICS434), and machine learning for big data (CSAI510).

# **Curriculum Development Collaborator Sydney Polytechnic Institute**

Sep 2020 - Mar 2021 Sydney, Australia

- Participated in curriculum development for a Master of Data Science.
- Designed lecture slides, assignments, practical sessions, and exams for courses: Database Systems and Infrastructure (MDS604), Mathematics for data science (MDS602), and Artificial Intelligence and Innovation (MDS607).

# System Engineer SABIC

Aug 2010 — May 2012 Jubail, Saudi Arabia

- In charge of securing and maintaining the plant network components.
- Upgraded obsolete network components during online operation.

#### Intern Saudi Aramco

Jun 2009 — Jan 2010 Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

- · Completed cooperative training at EXPEC ARC as a member of Computational Modeling Team.
- Developed a GUI interface populating the simulator output, large text files, into a database.

# Mashaan Alshammari

Last Updated: July 2024

Riyadh, Saudi Arabia mashaan.awad@outlook.com







## SELECTED PROJECTS

My YouTube Channel pytorch, jax, Jupyter

- I create videos explaining machine learning methods. The video starts by reading a paper or a book and ends with code.
- I cover topics like how a convolutional layer is implemented as matrix multiplication in pytorch.

#### **VisionTransformer-MNIST**

ViT, pytorch, Jupyter

- Implementation of "An Image is Worth 16x16 Words: Transformers for Image Recognition at Scale", published by Google research.
- Vision transformers replaces CNNs as the preferred method for image classification.

#### **Graph Convolutional Networks (GCNs)**

GNNs, GCNs, pytorch, Jupyter

- Implementation of the paper "Semi-Supervised Classification with Graph Convolutional Networks", which was published in ICLR 2017.
- Graph Convolutional Networks (GCNs) perform node classification in graphs.

**ADDA** 

GANs, pytorch, Jupyter

- Implementation of the paper "Adversarial Discriminative Domain Adaptation", which was published in CVPR 2017.
- ADDA uses GANs to perform unsupervised domain adaptation (UDA).

#### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- Mashaan Alshammari, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Graph Construction using Principal Axis Trees for Simple Graph Convolution.", arXiv:2302.12000, 2023.
- Mashaan Alshammari, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Random projection forest initialization for graph convolutional networks.", MethodsX, 2023.
- Mashaan Alshammari, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Random projection tree similarity metric for SpectralNet.", Array, 2023.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Adel F. Ahmed, Masahiro Takatsuka: "The Effect of Points Dispersion on the k-nn Search in Random Projection Forests.", IEEE Access, 2022.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, John Stavrakakis, Masahiro Takatsuka: "A Parameter-Free Graph Reduction for Spectral Clustering and Spectralnet.", Array, 2022.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>. John Stavrakakis, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Refining a k-nearest neighbor graph for a computationally efficient spectral clustering.", Pattern Recognition, 2021.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Approximate spectral clustering density-based similarity for noisy datasets.", Pattern Recognition Letters, 2019.
- <u>Mashaan Alshammari</u>, Masahiro Takatsuka: "Approximate spectral clustering with eigenvector selection and self-tuned k.", Pattern Recognition Letters, 2019.

#### SELECTED ACTIVITIES

#### **Journal Reviewer**

- Pattern Recognition Journal
- Neurocomputing Journal
- Information Sciences Journal

## **Conference Organization**

- Program committee, 30th International Conference on Neural Information Processing (ICONIP2023), Changsha, China, November 20-23, 2023.
- Technical Program Committee, 7th International Conference on Data Science and Machine Learning Applications (CDMA2022), Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, March 1-3, 2022.